hello it's
March 1st 2023
we're in cohort 2 of the paradol
textbook group
we're in meeting 18.
our first discussion on chapter eight
first
Michael if you wanted to just raise the
contacts or question that you wanted to
begin with and we'll just pick up there
you're I'm not sure if you're asking
sorry my microphone was off yes yeah so
uh the map territory fallacy I was
wondering what this is and whether you
could perhaps elaborate a little bit on
that fantasy
all right
I'm moving it to chapter nine even
though we're in chapter eight because
we're gonna bring in uh figure from
chapter 9.
um
oh you want to give a first
thought on on this
yeah sure
um actually map territory fallacy is um
one of the fallacies uh that is widely
used to sum up
um
somehow criticize a free energy
principle uh because uh as uh the
concept made the name of the concept may
suggest some believe that it's a kind of
fallacy to somehow
conflate the map with the territory so
by this I mean that free energy
principle claims that uh well we have
so very informally we have a map of the
principle or the theory or whatever and
the territory that it applies to so the
system or the agent that we're trying to
model but uh on the other hand by
claiming that the system or the agent
actually
does the kinds of inference that
recovers the map itself uh some people
believe that this kind of conflation
that map converts into territory or the
U vice versa is a fallacious claim so we
need to separate map from the territory
but uh in this uh recent paper on the
map territory fallacy fallacy
um
ramstead at all uh argued that actually
this is not a fallacy at all it is the
structure of these uh of the fep theory
so
in other words we're well aware that
there is a kind of uh inference as if
epistemology happening here so uh yeah
but
it's a bit more extensive they've lined
up
some number of arguments to defeat this
map territory fallacy fallacy and why
it's not fallacious at all so yeah
that's basically the gist of it in my
opinion
does it does it have to do with a
distinction between model and process
and the model is the
maybe the model is the map and the
no the other way the process is the map
and the model and the external world I
understand now the standard world is the
is the what is it the process is the
external world and the model is the
um I mean the generative model of the
agent itself right yeah it definitely
relates to that but on the other hand it
also relates to this concept of
self-evancing
which is
um
a way to describe the mechanism by which
uh the model in the environment and or
let's say the agent in the environment
models itself according to the
generative models so it's a kind of uh
as the name suggests a self-referential
way of modeling the system in the
environment
yes it's definitely a roller coaster and
not a resolved one
but still we can look to some of these
key recent works so the map territory
fallacy
would be
just like it's been since the classical
borgas writing
this realization like the map is not the
territory
kind of related like all models are
useful or some models are useful but not
are true like correlation is not
causation this sort of broad
space of aphorisms
that's basically like
instrumentalism isn't realism
as we might say it so that's the map
territory fallacy
would be making the fallacy that the map
is the territory I made a linear
regression between Cancer and heart
disease Ergo they are actually causal
that way
and when we're using octave inference
framework
one might be slightly more tempted than
the linear regression
to say well because I've generated
a model
that has a structure that seems to
articulate certain Natural Things
this is like an explanation
it might even have predictive power and
so that might lead somebody
to make this kind of a fallacy that the
map is the territory
um
then ramstead at all have kind of
agreed and Amplified
which is saying
actually when when you use the map
territory fallacy
to criticize the kind of cognitive
modeling
in the fep and Bayesian mechanics
you're acting fallaciously
and there's several angles on that
unpack more in the paper one angle is
you might be um
chopping off more than you want to
like you may realize it or not your
critique May extend to Simply all
quantitative modeling
and many people want to like
exercise fep
from the space of scientific modeling in
good graces
but then they don't want to for example
dismantle the architecture of using
statistics
so that's one angle which is like if you
actually
seek out the root of your descent
with this kind of cognitive modeling
you're going to be
cutting off a lot of what is just
understood to be statistical modeling
so it's like you've gone so far into
denying the map territory relationship
that you've actually
um biopsied more than just the fep
and then they go further which is that
um several features of the fep
make it the ideal model of generic
systems in statistical physics which is
a bit of an abstract statement so we can
bring it back to the textbook
with figure 9.1 which just as um uh
Michael brought up this came up in um
the par
recent bookstream with par where we we
asked what was happening
in this figure and and had some
discussion
um on it
and
here's the experimenter in the outer
shell
making a cognitive model
that cognitive model of let's just say
the rat and the teammates
has an aboutness
that reflects
the experimental setting and context
so it's making the experiments are human
in this outer shell is making a
cognitive model which is a map so all
the caveats of linear regressions apply
maps not the territory
don't want to fall into the map
territory fallacy
however it's also the case that that
cognitive model that map
is map like
in its relationality to the experimental
context
so there's this view from the outside
Black Box cognitive model being proposed
as a hypothesis
discrete Time chapter 7 continuous Time
chapter eight whatever it may be
but also the aboutness of that map
is about
this generative process
which is the generative process handing
stimuli to the generative model of the
agent
and so that duality
view from the inside and view from the
outside
makes the FTP uniquely
the ideal model of generic systems
so they're saying yeah for sure don't do
the naive fallacy
but don't engage in the fallacy fallacy
and then one final piece is if anyone
has a dissent with this let's just see
their alternative
let's not simply
tolerate
a standalone
criticism which is actually like a space
for improvement but is anyone seriously
proposing an alternative to this
structure
and the answer is not really Ali
I think it's just to add a slightly more
detail to uh with you what you just
explained in terms of the paper itself
well they actually
um
lay out two lines of arguments against
math territory fallacy one is a as I
mentioned uh the misconception that the
process and the model or the map and the
territory are conflated which they say
they're not actually conflated but the
territory behaves as if it were a map so
it's a kind of nested representation
and the other line of argument is as
Daniel mentioned
rises from a kind of misunderstanding of
the
uh
the kind of modeling used in statistical
physics and in particular the maximum
the principle of Maximum entropy
to model the environment so the way that
uh I mean in fep the way that agent
models or self evidences the environment
is through cmap or a constrained maximum
entropy principle so yeah I just wanted
to add those two bits of
detail there nice
Michael
so isn't isn't this that a map and a
territory implies that there is an
isometry between the map and the
territory
but in free energy
um in certain and several points they
claim these things are independent so
the the model the process and the model
is actually independent through these
Markov blankets and so on and we cannot
actually know what happens outside the
world
which is quite different from that idea
of map and territory
well great great questions I think
there's two there's two threads there
that are very tightly intertwined but
they're really important to to consider
separately so first you said is there an
isomorphism or an isometry
um
between the map and the territory
isomorphism in the strict sense meaning
identical structure
is not required
the generative process
even just talking about the map the
general process could be a continuous
variable and the generative model could
be like discrete or a binary categorical
variable so isometry is not even
required between the internal States and
the external States within the map
and then it's an even broader space
where you don't even know if isometry
even applies
to for example the structure of the real
territory so for sure
isometry or isomorphism is not required
some kind of
adaptive
resemblance
will come to be seen
that's like the good regulator theorem
from cybernetics any regulatory adaptive
system is as if that epistemology that
Ali mentioned it's as if it has an
effective model of its Niche again that
doesn't need to be isomorphic
but
Evolution or far from equilibrium
thermodynamics does make it the case
that you're going to get swept off the
table if you can't adapt
and so over generations and through
development it'll come to be the case
that there's functional
relationships
and a semiotic process
but it doesn't have to be astringent as
an isomorphism
and the second aspect was the
statistical Independence that is the
technical definition of a markup blanket
so Marco blanket it's the nodes
upon which two other sets of nodes in a
Bayesian graph are conditionally
independent
so the fact that we're invoking the base
graph right off the right off the bat we
know that we're talking about the map so
territories don't have Markov blankets
Maps do
so already we're within the map
discussion space
and with the Markov blanket does is it
precludes Direct
consequences direct causal impact from
internal and external States so no
telepathy no telekinesis
it's just a model constraint
however
still through the blankets there can be
the propagation of causal influences on
a base graph for example a light could
turn on in the generative process that
could shine photons onto the set State
and then that could update the beliefs
of the internal States
so
implications can still propagate on a
base graph
through the conditional Independence of
the markup blanket just like person a
could tell person B and then person B
could tell person C
and that doesn't mean that person a told
C yes Michael go for it
are you so you're talking about the free
energy principle but does it uh does
this apply also to the notion of maps
and territory as for instance we I mean
Google Maps for instance
they should have a more strict notion of
isometry I guess uh I'm I'm it's just a
question of what you were talking about
about the free energy principle or the
notion of maps and territory in general
so
to what extent does this metaphor do you
think that this metaphor really applies
to arbitrary depths
um
I I'm just for those who are watching
this video just have to like my screen
is like frozen so I'm just needing to
kind of
um reset the screen share but um
uh I mean arguably Google Maps it
depends on what you mean by an isometry
that's a two-dimensional
GPS landscape
so some kind of distorted
representation like making it flat
is done within the bounds of what's
useful
I'm not sure what what else needs to be
claimed for the purposes of Google Maps
okay and and so you're saying the same
also
applies to this uh these Markov blankets
and the free energy principle
what do you think Ali
again we go back again and again to
purses taxonomy of symbols
um actually Maps so
either I don't know Google Map or
circuit diagrams or these kinds of map
can act as a kind of icon for the object
instead of the index so
sorry I thought I got disconnected
um icon instead of index so an icon is a
kind of
um
sign that stands for the object
um through the relationship okay so uh
this kind of
um relation between the icon and the
object is a kind of structure preserving
mapping especially in the case of
geographical map maps or any other
cartographical different mappings
but uh in my opinion when we talk about
maps and territories
in relation with physical systems or
biological systems or whatever
we use this term in a slightly more uh
broader and a much more looser term and
it doesn't require to be an exactly
structure preserving mapping so it's
more like a mathematical mapping between
a mathematical relation between a sets
of object or sets of states and the
other sets of States namely generator
processes and the generative models so
that's it I mean there isn't a who need
any need to impose any additional
requirement for uh the exact structure
of those mappings it's a general
mathematical mapping per se
awesome yeah one other piece like from
the empirical practice side that I think
informs our philosophy of science is
very rarely is the empirical researcher
simply interested in producing
one final model
ing is almost always an iterative
process that involves the maintenance
and diversification and selection from
portfolios of models
so the findings of a paper might be like
this
phase space that we explored of models
these structural families suggest that
the two factors are better than the one
factor or that short-term memory does
interact with valence in this way
so right off the bat empirically we're
talking about portfolios of models
hence
there's obviously a multiple to one
mapping of maps to System of Interest
Ergo it's a bit Limited
to try to over interpret any map
and even get into this discussion of
whether it's actually the territory it's
not that's why we're doing it that's
statistics that's modeling
we have a whole host of models on our
computer none of them are the territory
but it's so tantalizing
because first off unlike the linear
regression we're talking about the
action perception Loop which brings this
sort of tangibility
within our grasp
and
um also there's this question of
language with the instrumentalism and
the realism
being mixed together
conceptually and linguistically
well the agent is minimizing free energy
is it though or is it the modeler's
generative model
of the actual embodied organism
so
somebody who knows that may be able to
speak or interpret flexibly and
understand that when people are talking
about an organism minimizing surprise or
the imperative for an organism to
minimize surprise
be able to on one hand lean into the
realism
and on the other hand lean into the
instrumentalism
but neither of those
I guess is like a standalone
interpretation or or straightforward
implication from any set of formalisms
let's go to chapter eight and let's see
how it plays out with continuous time
all right
as it's our um first discussion in eight
Let's uh
scan through
and then we'll come to the questions
next week
Okay so
everything flows nothing stands still
one of the cherished expressions
of
process philosophy and dynamicism
chapter 8 complement 7 by continuing the
discussion of generative models
chapter 7 was about discrete time
chapter 8 is on continuous State space
models
and it'll be brought up in multiple ways
that continuous time models
continuous perceptual models and
continuous action models
are often well suited for
proximate
generative models
not using a term formally but just like
dealing most proximally with incoming
sensory data
and on the action side dealing most
proximally with motor actuation
turns out that those
settings
often are continuous in nature like the
amount of pressure on a proprio receptor
or the amount of volume
by an auditory sensor
on the sensory sides and then on the
action side like the angle of an elbow
or the amount of force being exerted by
a muscle
those perceptual and motor
settings are really amenable to
continuous modeling
whereas discrete time models
are often amenable to categorical
symbolic and discrete settings
section 8.2 and just raise your hand if
you have like a want to add something or
a question 8.2
from chapter four
the generative model in continuous time
can be written as a pair of stochastic
equations determining how States hidden
States X generate data observables y
so that's the top equation is the data
are being generated
by a generator function on x hidden
States plus a noise term on y
and change in x x dot
derivative on X is a function of the
current state of X and V which are
slowly varying causes or contexts
plus a noise term on x
this is a classical formalization and in
the context of SPM and brain Imaging
this is like why is the fmri or the EEG
measurements
X are the unobserved neural States
neural activity Dynamics and there are
some sensor noise
and then the Dynamics of neural activity
which again are unobserved inferred from
data are a function of
current state of those neural activity
patterns and slowly varying causes which
might be like an attentional factor or
might be an experimental factor
and more broadly just this partition
into like signal and Noise
comes up again and again Ali
I just wanted to point out the the
second equation is also called Edo
stochastic differential equation so if
someone
come across that term that's exactly
this second equation
of 8.1
awesome
these stochastic calculi help us do
integrals and derivatives on
stochastic processes
action is absent from equation 8.1
this is because as outlined in the
recipe
action is part of the generative process
not the generative model
so this is potentially like saying the
consequences of action
are part of how things are actually
generated which is to say the generative
process even though action selection
is a function of a generative model
the consequences of action in terms of
modifying how the world changes
are occurring in the generative process
um
if we write down the Dynamics of the
real world the generative process
but of course this is like the Dynamics
of the map of the real world
we would have to include action so we
have a very similar equation but U is
now replaced
uh for V and there's bold G and F
um
this is a general formalization
with this sort of observable layer
caused by hidden States and the change
in the hidden States being related to
their current state and causal factors
so
they're going to specify in equation 8.3
a simple version that's compatible with
the above and noiseless
so it's a point attractor
when X is less than V the expected rate
of X is positive and vice versa so this
is a set point attractor
they're going to define a generative
process
where
action will change to fulfill the
predictions of 8.3
so this is an active movement
towards a point attractor
so that point attractor might reflect a
preferred Target for the eyes or a
preferred location
in space for a limb
and
this is going this is bringing us
from this totally general setting
into an active attainment
or an active agency exertion that's
compatible with those formalizations
they're going to take it one level more
complex
a more sophisticated model recognizes
that forces generated by muscles change
velocity not the position so you don't
just pick up and move your limb you're
actually modifying
a derivative of position which is Excel
Excel velocity and acceleration
and so here
we start to see a little bit of what
could be extended into higher and higher
derivatives with the generalized
coordinates of motion
but now f
of X and V
which is to say the function
that is a function of the current state
of the Hidden state
and the slowly causal uh varying factors
are going to be explicitly uh written as
this X1 is the position and X2 is the
velocity
now this generative model
is describing Hook's law so this is a
spring movement
with with a conservative spring
we can write down a general model that
predicts the Dynamics that wouldn't fold
if there was a spring drawing a limb to
a desired location
so that's like one level more advanced
than the uh Point attractor
which just linearly picks up the arm and
moves it to the point
now we have like this hooke's Law Spring
Force drawing and oscillating
and then we can imagine you can keep on
going you can have a damping spring and
so on
8.3
continuous time formalizations are well
suited to characterization of movements
and really just non-linear dynamical
systems
wherein discretization of time and space
is efficient
#livestream 52
discretization algorithms and
optimization
figure 8.1
we're returning to the spinal reflex
case
from chapter five
descending
predictions
getting mashed up with incoming
proprioceptive data
resulting in an error residual
that is modifying the trajectory of the
um actions in the face space shown here
X is the position of the limb
and V is where it's being drawn to
X is current position
V is the Target location
8.1
Precision attention and sensory
attenuation
we could talk more about it but this
related to a discussion that we had in
office hours last week
about the uh
sensory attenuation
here are some of our discussions
we talked about why it's relevant
to model
sensory attenuation
which is like the reduction of precision
on proprioception
in order to facilitate action selection
and that's also kind of described here
High precision sensor input you just get
shut down no movement is executed it's
catatonic
they're going to move into two classical
dynamical systems
one with
uh Predator prey like Dynamics lock
cover Volterra and the second with
chaotic Dynamics
Volterra
Predator prey model also called a
winnerless competition
equation 8.6 gives the lock of Volterra
Dynamics
and here on the top is the winnerless
competition amongst plant herbivore and
carnivore
also one could imagine this is like
activity patterns in the fmri OR EEG
with different brain regions
and that's exactly how it's been used
and here is the phase space this is like
three three lines plotted on time axis
but we can also think about that as a
trajectory in a three-dimensional space
so some sort of Cube and these there's
just one point
a b c or phc
that are moving in this
three-dimensional space on some
trajectory and then here if you look at
one side or the other of a cube
you can look at how there's something
like a a slowly drifting limit cycle
when you project down to a given axis
now they're going to move that
lockabletera winnerless competition
Predator pre-dynamic into sequential
action
here's how sequential action has been
used
in iblink conditioning experiments
and in writing generation of sequential
information
patterns and also in the par
bookstream 2.1
there was a great discussion
by Thomas so he said early octave it was
continuous
it was generalized filtering and then
there was the engagement with action
people started thinking about how to get
sequential Dynamics
emergence of sequences from continuous
Dynamics was a key step towards
purposeful planning
that's figure 8.3
then it's like okay that's all good for
making this kind of
semi-regularized scribble
but what if you wanted actual policy
selection on which word to write
that's going to be really hard to bake
into a lock of ultera model
so
things moved into the explicit discrete
State space model with the pomdp
formalization
and that led to planning as inference
and all these other features and now
we're moving back into these hybrid and
hierarchical models where continuous
State spaces are reintroduced as a low
level of hierarchical modeling
um
8.2 learning continuous models
continuous State spaces are a lot like
discrete State spaces in discrete State
spaces you're basically taking a sum
across a finite number of entities in
continuous State spaces you're taking an
integral from here to there
and there are different approximations
that facilitate those integrals
the pmdp formalization of chapter 7 has
largely superseded the use of
generalized lockabletera systems in
active
but it's still extremely didactic and
pedagogical
and used in the lower levels of
hierarchical models
now they're going to move from the
lockableterra to the Lorenz attractor
system
which has some parameters that are
reflective of weather systems
that's been studied in the context of
Birdsong
and they're going to use the lorenza
tractor in the Birdsong case
to talk about generalized synchrony so
generalized synchrony doesn't mean lock
step synchronization
it means that there are entities whose
Dynamics are on a manifold
in other words their Dynamics are not
untethered from each other there's
Mutual information such that they're
co-ambulating on a lower dimensional
manifold so the Birdsong example has
been in multiple
papers
it's a chaotic attractor that's
underlying the emission of Birdsong by
the two birds
livestream 32
is on couples
chaotic systems so that's where the math
are unpacked the most
but here we can just see
on the right side of figure 8.5 that
after learning
there's a tightening
of the first and the second Bird's
expectations
towards a manifold
it's called singing from the same hymn
sheet briston's quite fond of that
phrasing
and each bird contributes sections of
the song and there's some interesting uh
connections back to sensory attenuation
again
section 8.5 goes into hybrid discrete
and continuous models which we've
basically been talking about multiple
times so figure 8.6 first off note that
the G should be connected to the pi
then note the fractal rake structure
we have the
rake here
figure 4.3 on the bottom
continuous time v x x Prime double Prime
and so on
but these continuous time models lower
half of figure 4.3
are embedded within a discrete time
higher level
a b
d s t minus 1 t t plus one
so
we see both parts of figure 4.3 discrete
time on top
d b a
past present and future
and now we're seeing it as a top level
nesting
continuous time lower level model
and here x derivative of x second
derivative on x
key difference between discrete time and
continuous time models
Michael
yeah I have a question what happens if
the embedded time frames are not fitting
into the upper
frame so if for instance here the lower
parts overlap with the um with the
states of the upper part so if you have
a time frame and maybe and
chopping up of time into segments but
the segments overlap
is there a possibility to model such
kinds of things yeah a few thoughts good
question the first is that the
continuous time model
doesn't make explicit predictions about
the future
The Continuous time model is a lot like
a Taylor series approximation so
although it embodies through the
generalized coordinates which are one
two and three shown here but could be up
to six or more
it embodies
some patterns that extend beyond the
presence but the continuous time
formalization is actually always real
Time That's one answer
a more empirical answer is if you have a
model
where
um there's like sort of clashing time
scales
you're going to end up with
multicollinearity
in fitting the data to empirical results
so you'll get a variety of model fitting
aberrations
because the variance is going to be
partitioned in a sort of
uh discordant way
so some random seed might partition a
lot of the variants up here and then
another random seed partitions it down
here
so if there's Discord and overlap you're
just going to end up with a headache
trying to get that model to be useful
so no one's going to stop you but that
doesn't mean that it's going to be an
effective architecture for actual
parameterization
so does it mean we need to squeeze
somehow
the stuff into these boxes into these
rectangles embedded rectangles there's
no not really a way to have these
overlapping boxes there what's the case
that we're thinking about because pretty
much here is the movement of time at
some click
and then this could be every second is
when the new limb location is chosen
and then within each second
there's the continuous movement of the
limb
yeah so so for instance they talk about
a sentence so we have words and
sentences paragraphs um texts and so on
but now if you look at prosodic features
they may overlap with sentence
boundaries so you wouldn't have a kind
of pause structure that is fits into the
sentence structure there could be two
different
ways of chopping up the sentence in in
acoustic way and
um well in a you know in in terms of
words and sentences and so on
I think it's a super interesting
question which is like this strict
nesting like well isaacades continuously
let's just say
and they're recognizing letters okay
letters are strictly nasty within words
words are strictly necessary than
sentences paragraphs and so on
and one might want to go oh and
paragraphs are strictly nested within
narratives it's like well no not
necessarily
there might be a narrative boundaries
that are up down left right of the
paragraphs so let's see it start by just
graphing it how you see it
and then let's go from there but in
principle it's not going to be
addressable
but when you actually write it out you
may discover
again a portfolio of model structures
which can be used empirically
to differentiate hypotheses
and their Maps so maybe it turns out
that a simpler model where prosody is
sentence delimited
is more effective because there's so
fewer parameters so the Bayesian
information Criterion favors that model
but that doesn't mean that prosody is
sentenced to Limited it means that
a statistical structure with sentence to
limited prosody was selected for
information theoretic purposes
map territory
but we want to say things about the
territory
so that's always the challenge we do a
regression between
foraging activity and the humidity
and we want to say when it's more humid
the ants forage more
that seems like the natural thing to say
and it might be our motivating question
but it's always hard to remember that
it's like ah higher values in the
humidity measure are correlated with
higher foraging activity it's like just
say that foraging increases with more
humidity
but that is the
departure point of the map territory
fallacy
so
it's often more resolvable than people
want to know in the specifics
that's the deflationary perspective
and less resolvable than we want to know
in principle
Ollie
and also one reason behind formulating
sorry the continuous Dynamics in terms
of a Taylor series is because it also
Maps uh onto the lagrangian formulation
of mechanics because one of the reasons
lagrangian's
mechanics is used instead of the
traditional Newtonian mechanics is to
just get rid of time parameters so
instead of time they use momentum and
also the lagrangian so we don't need
time explicitly defined or described in
order to account for the behavior of the
trajectories or to describe the
behaviors of the trajectories what all
we need is this series of
a successive differentiations in terms
of Taylor series
to be able to describe the whole
behavior of the system because
accounting explicitly for time parameter
is much difficult to model than
than describing these dynamical systems
in terms of their generalized
coordinates in other words they're
lagrangian formulations and in the path
integral formulation of fep that's
basically the solution
proposed by Dalton person and others to
use lagrangian formulation to describe
these systems nice good point
um
equation 8.8
is describing the
transformation
from the discrete Target selection of
the upper level of this model
and the way that that is received
by The Continuous time model so here the
discrete time Target selection
is then received by The Continuous time
icicade model
that is an experimental setting that has
been studied relatively extensively
here in the middle of figure 8.7
we see the target selection being
modeled
and the cicading
and here's the
calling back to that spring-like
movement here's like the acceleration
and then the dampening
as the target is fixed upon
so isocating has been studied relatively
extensively
in the context of information driven
continuous modeling
box 8.3 is a bit of a side note
on discretization so a gaussian mixture
model or very related is a k means model
where one takes a cluster of data points
in space and asks how many clusters k
fit
this
scattering of points you could just have
one K with just a point in the center
and then there's some variance
distribution around it or you could say
2K and then you can look at the error
profiles to determine uh a adequate
number of clusters
somewhere between one cluster and one
cluster per data point there's going to
be a k means value that is like
statistically optimal
8.6
in this chapter which is relatively
short
and in some ways kind of
introducing the continuous time
formalism so that we can get to these
important topics like Hybrid models
they overview applications of continuous
time GMS
this is a huge topic and much has been
left out see table 8.1
synthetic bird song
ocular motor delay conditioned reflex
smooth Pursuit eye movement 2012.
psychosis illusions 2012.
cicades
many papers
action observation
attention
hybrid discrete continuous models
self-organization
it's a foundation for further
exploration
they focused on movement prediction
it simplifies the treatment of motor
control we don't need any additional
Machinery or inverse models and this was
also a topic picked up in the skilled
performance
discussion of hippolito at all
talking about interactionism rather than
instructionalism
they talked about the lock of Volterra
winnerless competition Predator prey and
the lorenza tractor chaotic system in
all those cases it was possible to find
this concept of generalized synchrony
which isn't lockstep but it's like a
mutual information or uh manifold
controversal
and then they introduced the Hybrid
models which tend to have continuous
lower level Dynamics and discrete higher
level Dynamics
that's it for today next time we're
going to come back to chapter nine
which is going to
um be talking about model based data
analysis fitting models to data
and
next week uh we'll do chapter 8
questions
and come through it again in preview
nine so
thank you fellows see you next time